CURRICULUM VITAE

William Esco (W. E.) Moerner

Harry S. Mosher Professor and Professor, by courtesy, of Applied Physics Department of Chemistry, Biophysics Program, and Molecular Imaging Program Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305-5080

650-723-1727 (phone), 650-725-0259 (fax), e-mail: wmoerner@stanford.edu

Education

1975	B.S. Physics (Final Honors) B.S. Electrical Engineering (Final Honors) A.B. Mathematics (summa cum laude)	Washington University St. Louis, Missouri
1978	M.S. (Physics)	Cornell University Ithaca, New York
1982	Ph.D. (Physics)	Cornell University Ithaca, New York
	Thesis Topic: Vibrational Relaxation Dynamics of an IR-Laser-Excited	

Molecular Impurity Mode in Alkali Halide Lattices

Thesis Advisor: Professor A. J. Sievers

Career Summary

2014-	Faculty Fellow, ChEM-H at Stanford	
2011-2014	Chemistry Department Chair	
2005-	Professor, by courtesy, of Applied Physics	
2002-	Harry S. Mosher Professor of Chemistry	
1998-	Professor of Chemistry, Stanford University	
1995-1998	First Holder, Distinguished Chair in Physical Chemistry, Department of	
	Chemistry and Biochemistry, University of California San Diego	
1989-1995	Research Staff Member and Project Leader, IBM Almaden Research Center	
	San Jose, California	
1993-1994	Visiting Guest Professor, Laboratory for Physical Chemistry, ETH Zentrum	
	(Swiss Federal Institute of Technology), Zürich, Switzerland	
1988-1989	Manager, Laser-Materials Interactions, IBM Almaden Research Center	
	San Jose, California	
1981-1988	Research Staff Member, IBM Almaden Research Center, San Jose, California	
1975-1981	Graduate Research Assistant and NSF Graduate Fellow Laboratory for Atomic and Solid State Physics, Cornell University, Ithaca, New	
	York	

Honors and Awards

Wu Zheng Kai Chemistry Prize, Fudan University, 2018

Distinguished Eagle Scout Award, 2017

Photonics Pioneer Award, Duke University Fitzpatrick Institute for Photonics, 2016

Distinguished Alumnus Award, Washington University, St. Louis, 2015

Julio Palmaz Award for Innovation in Healthcare and Biosciences, Biomed SA, 2015

Fellow, SPIE-The International Society for Optics and Photonics, 2015

Honorary Fellow, Royal Society of Chemistry, 2015

Nobel Prize in Chemistry, 2014

John Gamble Kirkwood Medal for Outstanding Achievement in Science, from Yale University and the New Haven Section of the American Chemical Society, 2013

Engineering Alumni Achievement Award, Washington University, 2013

Peter Debye Award in Physical Chemistry, 2013

Pittsburgh Spectroscopy Award, 2012

Irving Langmuir Prize in Chemical Physics, 2009

Wolf Prize in Chemistry, 2008

Member, National Academy of Sciences, 2007

Fellow, American Association for the Advancement of Science, 2004

Geoffrey Frew Fellow, Australian Academy of Sciences, 2003

Fellow, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 2001

Earle K. Plyler Prize for Molecular Spectroscopy, American Physical Society, 2001

Robert Burns Woodward Visiting Professor, Department of Chemistry, Harvard University, 1997-1998

IBM Outstanding Technical Achievement Award for Single-Molecule Detection and Spectroscopy, November 22, 1992

Fellow, American Physical Society, November 16, 1992

Fellow, Optical Society of America, May 28, 1992

Senior Member, IEEE, June 17, 1988

IBM Outstanding Technical Achievement Award (with R. M. Macfarlane and R. M. Shelby) for Photon-Gated Spectral Hole-Burning, July 11, 1988

National Winner of the Roger I. Wilkinson Outstanding Young Electrical Engineer Award for 1984, from the electrical engineering honorary society, Eta Kappa Nu, April 22, 1985

Doctor Honoris Causa

University Aix Marseille, November 9, 2016 University of Chile, December 10, 2015

Honorary Professorships

Moscow State Pedagogical University, August 2018 Fudan University, July 2018

Named Lectureships

Jin Si Lecture, Fudan University, China, July 2018

Hermann Anton Haus Lecture, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, April 2018

Nelson Lecture, The University of Miami, April 2018

E. U. Condon Lecture, University of Colorado, Boulder, Colorado, February 2018

Munushian Lecture, Ming Hsieh Department of Electrical Engineering, Viterbi School of Engineering, University of Southern California, February 2017

Morris Travers Memorial Lecture, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, January 2017

Andreas C. Albrecht Memorial Lecture, Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Cornell University, April 2016

Hightower Lecture, Department of Physics, Emory University, April 2016

Fred J. Robbins Memorial Lectures, Department of Chemistry, Pomona College, March 2016

Provost Lecture, Temple University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, March 2016

Wallace H. Coulter Lecture, Pittcon, Atlanta, Georgia, March 2016

Paul D. Gottlieb Lecture, Institute of Cellular and Molecular Biology, The University of Texas at Austin, February 2016

Sir Ernst Chain Lecture, Imperial College of London, November 2015

Samuel I. Weissman Memorial Lectures, Department of Chemistry, Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri, November 2015

Presidential Distinguished Lecture, The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio, September 2015

Presidential Distinguished Lecture, The University of Texas at San Antonio, September 2015 Paul C. Cross Lecture, Department of Chemistry, University of Washington, May 2015

George B. Kistiakowsky Lecturer, Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Harvard University, March 2015

John Gamble Kirkwood Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, Yale University, September 2013 Walter Kauzmann Lecturer in Biophysical Chemistry, Princeton University, September 2013

E. K. C. Lee Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of California, Irvine, May 2013 Samuel Krimm Lecture in Biophysics, University of Michigan, April 2013

Ehrenfest Colloquium Lecturer (repeat), University of Leiden, The Netherlands, June 2012

Pittsburgh Conference Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of Pittsburgh, 2011 Leica Scientific Forum United Kingdom Lecturer, June 2011

Willis Flygare Memorial Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 2011

Joe L. Franklin Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, Rice University, 2010

William Lloyd Evans Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, The Ohio State University, 2009

Karl Friedrich Bonhoeffer Lecturer, Max Planck Institute for Biophysical Chemistry, Göttingen, Germany, 2009

Neil Gordon Frontiers in Chemistry Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, Wayne State University, 2009

A. S. Noyes Lecturer, Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, University of Texas at Austin, 2009

DuPont-Marshall Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of Pennsylvania, 2008

Herbert H. King Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, Kansas State University, 2006

Edwin Yunker Lecturer, Department of Physics, Oregon State University, 2006

A. R. Gordon Distinguished Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of Toronto, 2006

- Lecturer, Summer School on Visualization, Manipulation, and Modeling of Single Biomolecules, ENS Paris, France, 2005
- Geoffrey Frew Fellowship Lecturer, Australian Academy of Sciences (University of Queensland, Australian National University, Swinburne Institute of Technology, University of Melbourne), 2003
- International Invited Lecturer (Basel, Berne, Lausanne, Geneva): Conference Universitaire de Suisse Occidentale du 3ème Cycle en Chimie, 2003

Moses Gomberg Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of Michigan, 2001

William Draper Harkins Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of Chicago, 2001 Guest Lecturer in Frontiers in Spectroscopy, Ohio State University, 1999

Arthur D. Little Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1995

Ehrenfest Colloquium Lecturer, University of Leiden, The Netherlands, March 1994 Samuel M. McElvain Lecturer, Department of Chemistry, University of Wisconsin, 1993

Patents

- U. S. Patent 4,614,116: "Phase Sensitive Ultrasonic Modulation Method for the Detection of Strain-Sensitive Spectral Features", September 30, 1986.
- U. S. Patent 5,064,264: "Photorefractive Materials", November 12, 1991.
- U. S. Patent 5,361,148: "Apparatus for Photorefractive Two-Beam Coupling," November 1, 1994.
- U. S. Patent 5,460,907: "Photorefractive Materials", October 24, 1995.
- U. S. Patent 5,607,799: "Optical Photorefractive Article," March 4, 1997.
- U. S. Patent 6,046,925: "Photochromic Fluorescent Proteins and Optical Memory Storage Devices Based on Fluorescent Proteins," April 4, 2000.
- U. S. Patent 6,280,884: "Process for Photorefractive Index Grating Formation," August 28, 2001.
- U. S. Patent 7,068,698 "Room-Temperature Source of Single Photons Based on a Single Molecule in a Condensed Matter Host," June 27, 2006.
- U. S. Patent 8,057,655: "Sub-Micron Object Control Arrangement and Approach Therefor," Nov. 15, 2011 (provisional application filed August 20, 2004).
- U. S. Patent 8,153,446 B2: "Fluorogenic Compounds Converted to Fluorophores by Photochemical or Chemical Means and Their Use in Biological Systems," April 10, 2012 (provisional application filed May 23, 2008).
- U. S. Patent 8,693,742 B2: "Three-Dimensional Single-Molecule Fluorescence Imaging Beyond the Diffraction Limit Using a Double-Helix Point Spread Function," April 8, 2014 (provisional application filed December 17, 2008).
- U. S. Patent 8,772,048 B2: "Fluorogenic Compounds Converted to Fluorophores by Photochemical or Chemical Means and Their Use in Biological Systems," July 8, 2014 (provisional application filed May 23, 2008).
- U. S. Patent 9,075,010 B2: "Enhancement of Molecular Emission Using Optical-Antenna Structures," July 7, 2015 (provisional application filed October 15, 2010).
- U. S. Patent 9,693,034 B2: "Apparatus and Method for Localizing Objects for Distance and/or in Three Dimensions Using a Spiral Point Spread Function," June 27, 2017, Disclosure filed May 17, 2012, Provisional filed December 13, 2011.
- U. S. Patent 10,187,626: "Apparatuses and Methods for Three-Dimensional Imaging of an Object," January 22, 2019, Provisional filed April 10, 2015.

Application: "Firefly Luciferin Analogues, Methods of Making Firefly Luciferin Analogues, and Methods of Imaging," Provisional filed March 10, 2009.

Additional published disclosures in optics, frequency domain optical storage, single-molecule applications, microscopy, and photorefractive materials.

Professional Societies and Positions

Boards:

Member, Scientific Advisory Board, Welch Foundation, 2017-

Member, World Laureates Association, 2017-

Member, Board of Trustees of the Society for Science and the Public, 2018

Journals:

International Advisory Board, Angewandte Chemie, 2017-

Associate Editor, Quarterly Reviews of Biophysics-Discovery 2015-2016

Advisory Editor, ChemPhysChem 2004-2018

Advisory Editor, Chemical Physics Letters 1998-2016

Editorial Advisory Board, Journal of Physical Chemistry 2013-2015

Advisory Editor, Single Molecules 2000-2002

American Academy of Arts and Sciences

American Association for the Advancement of Science

American Chemical Society

Program Committee, Symposium on Optical Properties of Polymers, August 1996

Single-Molecule Symposium Organizer, Physical Chemistry Division, April 1997

Co-Editor, Special Issue of *Accounts of Chemical Research* on Single Molecules and Ions, December 1996

American Physical Society

Chair, Herbert P. Broida Prize Committee 2000

Member, Earle K. Plyler Prize Committee 2001

Member, Irving Langmuir Prize Committee 2010

Symposium Organizer for Laser Science Topical Group, 1992 March Meeting

Symposium Organizer for Laser Science Topical Group, 1993 March Meeting

Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers, Lasers and Electro-Optics Society

Assistant Treasurer, 1988 Annual Meeting

Treasurer and Program Committee Member, 1989 Annual Meeting

Symposium Organizer, LEOS 1989 Annual Meeting on Optical Memory and Storage

Materials Research Society

National Academy of Sciences

Optical Society of America

Chair, Fundamental and Applied Spectroscopy Technical Group, 1992-1994

General Chair and Founder, OSA Topical Conference on Persistent Spectral Hole-Burning Science and Applications, 1991

Co-Editor, 2 Special Issues of J. Opt. Soc. America B on Persistent Spectral Hole-Burning

Advisory Chair and Program Committee Member, Topical Meeting on Spectral Hole-Burning and Luminescence, 1993-1994

Assistant Chair, Fundamental and Applied Spectroscopy Technical Group, 1992

Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers

Program Co-Chair, Symposium on Organic Photorefractive Materials, 1996, 1997, 1998 Program Committee, 1999-2003

Conference on Quantum Electronics and Laser Science

Program Committee, 1992 and 1993

Conference on Lasers and Electro-Optics

Program Committee, 1999

International Conference on Hole-Burning and Single-Molecule Spectroscopies Program Committee, 1996, 1999, 2003

Gordon Research Conference on Single-Molecule Approaches to Biology, Co-Vice Chair, 2008; Co-Chair, 2010.

Task Forces and Major University Committees

Chairman, IBM Task Force on Frequency Domain Optical Storage, 1984.

Physics and Mechanisms Member, IBM Task Force on Holographic Optical Storage, 1986.

Co-Chair, Systems and Applications, IBM Optical Storage Initiative, 1988.

Member, Appointments and Promotions Committee, Division of Humanities and Sciences, Stanford University, 2002-2004.

Member, Nanoinitiative Committee, Stanford University, Winter 2006

Member, NSF Center for Probing the Nanoscale Executive Committee, Fall 2007

Member, Stanford University Committee on Health and Safety, 2007-2008

Chair, Stanford University Committee on Health and Safety, 2008-2009, 2009-2010

Member, Stanford University Emergency Management Steering Committee, 2009-2010

Member, Advisory Board, Center for Biological Imaging at Stanford, 2010-2015

Member, Corporation Visiting Committee, Department of Chemistry, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2013-2017.

Study Panels and Governmental Committees

Member, NSF SBIR Study Panel, September, 1996.

Member, NIH Bioengineering Symposium Panel on Imaging at the Molecular and Cellular Levels, February 27-28, 1998.

Co-Chair, Toward Molecular Scale Devices Subgroup, NSF Integrating Themes Workshop for Physical Chemists, September 18-20, 1998, Keystone, Colorado.

Member, NIH Review Panel, November 1999; September 2000.

Member, FAMOS Update Panel, National Research Council, 1999-2002.

Member, NIH-NIGMS Workshop on Single Molecule Detection and Manipulation, 2000

Member, NSF-Intelligence Community Workshop on Approaches to Combat Terrorism, 2002.

Subgroup Chair, NIH-NIDA Workshop on Emerging Technologies: Analysis of Endogeneous Biomaterials and Single-Molecule Studies, 2002.

Member, International Review Committee for the Institute of Atomic and Molecular Sciences (IAMS) of Academia Sinica, Taiwan, 2003-2004

Member, NIH-BST Molecular Imaging Study Section, 2004.

Member, Pacific Northwest National Laboratory DOE-BES Review Panel, 2005.

Member, DOE Workshop on Single-Molecule Research in the New Millenium, 2005.

Member, Advisory Board, Institute of Atomic and Molecular Sciences (IAMS) of Academia Sinica, Taiwan, 2005-

Session Chair: NIH Frontiers in Live Cell Imaging Conference, April 19-21, 2006

Member, NIH-NHGRI Study Section, July, 2006

Member, Board of Scientific Counselors, National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering, 2010-2014